thank you uh so much Stephen for having
me once again it's uh always good to be
doing these webinars especially on this
topic which I find so interesting and uh
and fascinating as we will delve into
this so if for those who are around for
part one this is as you can see from the
title a part two so for the topics of
pregnant alone DHEA and thyroid you can
check out that previous webinar and
today's webinar will focus on estrogen
HCG infertility now I do have an ebook
by the title Beyond trt you can check
that out if you want a referenceable
guide It's very cheap it's on my website
but I will fully disclose that there is
nothing in the book that I am not going
to talk about today you won't get any
bonus content from buying my book you
will just get a referenceable guide that
you can refer back to so there will
probably be more content in this webinar
than what's in the book because I get a
chance to ji a jabber for a good hour so
let's uh let's get into this so just
going to start with a with a couple of
introductory points here so estrogen HCG
and fertility are by far the three most
controversial topics in the trt space
so it is okay if you hear something in
this webinar that you disagree with that
is totally fine I am presenting my
opinions and there are varying opinions
on these topics from practitioners and
health coaches in this space who I have
a huge amount of respect for and I think
it's important that we can agree to
disagree on certain topics especially
topics like this which are not so cut
and dry and straightforward as you'll
see in this presentation so I'm going to
get this one out of the way I am not a
doctor and this content is educational
advice to discuss with your health coach
and or doctor so down the line during
the presentation when I refer to working
with clients dosing Etc it is all
implied that this is educational advice
given to the client to then speak to
that doctor or health coach about so I'm
going to give a quick shout out to my
friend Ellie Gilbert she did not pay me
to do this but as I am not using her
studio today I am going to give her a
shout out because she could not be here
with me um a lot of the time in this
topic I'm going to reference The
Importance of Being Fit being healthy
and having low body fat and my friend
Alli has a great uh gpp for trt program
designed to help guys get in shape when
they start their trt treatment which is
so critically important not just for how
you look in the mirror but how you
actually respond to treatment so quick
plug for her she's also a partner with
marrick so you can check her out and all
the good stuff that she is doing I'm
going to dive straight into this this
content is a little bit dry there is an
absolute huge amount of stuff for me to
get through I am going to whirl through
it pretty quickly and then I'm going to
take questions at the end so the first
of the controversial Triad estrogen so
as I prefaced earlier estrogen
management and the role of estrogen in
men and the side effects on trt which
are often labeled as
estrogenic encompasses the most
contentious topic on the internet this
is the topic that people say all kinds
of horrific things back and forth about
each other to there's almost Cults for
certain sides of this equation there's a
lot of dogmatic views on certain things
and there's a lot of discussions which I
think aren't as helpful for getting to
the bottom of actually helping guys feel
better and respond properly to trt which
is the whole damn point of this anyway
I'm doing my best not to swear
excessively so estrogen questions and
debates form the majority of the
discourse surrounding trt online in
forums and groups and as testosterone
replacement therapy has become more
popular More welln you know back in my
day there was maybe one YouTube video or
one YouTube channel and maybe one or two
books on it now there is so much
conflicting data and conflicting
information I think it can be very
overwhelming so I'm going to do my best
to distill down this very complex topic
into about 20 minutes so these are the
key points that I think you need to
consider when considering estrogen on
trt firstly and this is the foundation
is optimal physiological levels of
testosterone in men should not
necessitate the need for pharmaceutical
inhibition of aromatase which is the
enzyme that forms estrogen this just
doesn't biologically make sense so men
who naturally have testosterone levels
in the upper quartile of the reference
range or Beyond will actually often in
in my observations working with these
guys who who don't need trt or even
close they actually have serum estadio
levels well beyond the reference range
as well and their serum aradial levels
are very similar to men who are on trt
who are not blocking the aritas enzyme
so many negative symptoms which come
from trt which I will now be referring
to moving forward as cite effects occur
in men who are in a state where they
would not be naturally making the amount
of testosterone that they are
administering if they could and thus are
creating superphysiological levels of
testosterone to their individual body
what on Earth did I just say what I'm
saying here is that very often I see men
and I'm sure that Mar Health sees plenty
of men as well in this kind of scenario
who come in who are overweight they're
off track in their life they may be
drinking too much alcohol they may be
eating too much junk food they may be
not looking after themselves the way
they should be and they might not have
been looking after themselves for a
while and this has induced a state of
secondary hypogonadism so what's
happening is the body is actively
suppressing testosterone production and
if we come in and go okay we're going to
now inject the optimal amount of
testosterone that a man your age should
have it's kind of like we're coming in
with a Ferrari engine and we're putting
it into a Suzuki Swift that needs a
service and we're expecting it to just
morph into a sports car and drive the
way a sports car will and when we talk
about superphysiological meaning beyond
the physiology that could natur
naturally be achieved what's important
is about what is physiological or super
physiological for an individual so the
version of a of a man if we took the
exact same guy and he was cloned and
there were two different versions of him
in one he'd look after himself
immaculately and in another one he
absolutely trashed his health the
optimal physiological amount of
testosterone for the latter man would be
at a much lower sealing level because
someone who is not looking after
themselves in the body who is is
naturally suppressing this production
they have no business having
testosterone levels beyond the reference
range it is physiologically impossible
and this creates a disconnect between
what the patient or client is doing with
their trt and what their body can
actually naturally tolerate and I think
that this is a very important and underd
discussed area that causes a lot of side
effects on testosterone is that the
individual either hasn't had the chance
to do the work or hasn't understood the
value of doing the work to meet the
testosterone levels and to actually be
able to earn the testosterone levels
that they are administering into their
body so many of the side effects as as I
just alluded to of trt come from not
resolving the root cause of why
testosterone was low in the first place
or the maladaptive diet and lifestyle
habits which have Arisen as a behavioral
response to the prolonged state of
hypogonadism one of the issues that
comes to light when you work with men is
the fact that we are humans and when you
feel like [__] you are more drawn to it
doesn't make you but it it gives you a a
stronger predisposition towards doing
things that are [__] for you that make
you feel better in the short term drugs
alcohol junk food other hedonistic vices
which over time acre into having a
further detriment to your health so it's
like a vicious cycle and so what we have
to look at is going okay well are we in
a situation where we haven't resolved
the root cause of what caused the lowy
testosterone in the first place or we
still need to actually work on and
consistently improve the poor diet
lifestyle behavioral patterns which have
which the individual has become
accustomed to practicing because they've
felt like crap for so long so cadal is a
proxy for systemic estrogen activity as
a paracrine hormone and it is not
accurately measured as testosterone when
even when using a sensitive assay so
when we're measuring the estrogen that's
floating around in the bloodstream when
you get a blood draw done doesn't matter
how sensitive the panel is it's
important to understand that estrogen is
actually made locally in the tissue it's
a paracrine hormone whereas testosterone
is an endocrine hormone
which circulates so the amount of
testosterone that we're measuring in the
blood is a more meaningful measure than
the amount of estrogen that we're
measuring but I don't think that means
that the number of estrogen that we're
looking at is completely redundant and
useless and means absolutely El Zilo
it's relevant but it's aoxy
so one thing that I think we should all
be looking at and I know that marrick
practices this and all clinics who know
what they're doing practice this is that
increasing injection frequency is the
number one intervention for resolving
these side effects if you can smooth out
the injection frequency and create less
Peaks and troughs you're going to have a
better response to treatment and I think
that one of the key determining factors
my personal opinion is that how well an
individual is doing with their Baseline
Health should be a primary determinant
of injection frequency so if you're not
doing too well and you've started trt I
think you're going to be more sensitive
to the Peaks and troughs than someone
whose health is holistically and overall
better so another thing that guys can
look at and practitioners can look at is
the idea of using a transcrotal
compounded cream for trt if the
individual isn't particularly poor
health and particularly predisposed of
these side effects because of the
greater preferential conversion to DHT
and this can often be better tolerated
by men who are starting to do the work
on their health Journey but need to
optimize their testosterone in the
process so what's very important though
is you can inject every day if you want
to you can do twice a day application to
transcrotal cream you can inject as
often as you possibly can but this is a
Band-Aid
solution while you also do the work to
address the lifestyle interventions that
are actually going to resolve the
underlying root cause of why you're
having these issues in the first place
because if you're having these issues
it's not just going to affect your trt
it's going to affect your health overall
massively particularly disposing you
towards the four primary diseases of
Aging which is cancer heart disease
dementia and
diabetes
so this is commonly again in my
experience caused by insulin resistance
and or obesity which often occur
concurrently liver disease is a big one
and alcoholism plays into that
hypothyroidism as I mentioned in Beyond
trt part one T3 is a key regulator of
aritas SSRI medications due to
interactions with prolactin as well as
other
mechanisms as well as combination of all
of these factors because a lot of the
time these things occur together so if
insulin resistance is identified as the
root cause for why there's excessive
rheumatiz I'm just going to throw this
out there if someone is going to use a
pharmaceutical intervention it makes
much more sense in my opinion again not
a medical doctor so I can't prescribe
anything to use metformin because
metformin is not only something that
decreases a ratas production in diabetes
you can Google meformin aatase if you
want to fact check me on that it will
come up right at the top of Google for
you
but this is actually an evidence-based
pharmaceutical medication to employ not
aromatase Inhibitors which are not
evidencebased in men especially longterm
especially on trt so it's important to
look that look at the fact that every
study showing the benefit of trt and I'm
borrowing this from Dr Neil
ruser has been done without blocking or
modulating aromitas even in health
compromised patient populations there
are no studies in the medium to long
term assessing the health outcomes the
overall health outcomes of men on trt
while modulating aritas there's none
this is not evidence-based this is
broscience so men who trial aritas
Inhibitors to solve their problems from
in my observations might fix a couple of
short-term things short-term subjective
things but they often create more
problems in the process such as joint
pain sexual dysfunction and brain fog
and then what I see years than they
reach for supplements or further
medications to try to remedy this and I
think that something that people should
avoid in the pursuit of Optimal Health
again just my opinion is using drugs to
counteract the side effects of other
drugs so my personal conclusion when it
comes to aritas Inhibitors is that it's
important to consider the unknowns of
pharmaceutical interventions when
considering risk to reward ratio I.E if
you're addressing that something is an
unknown I think that level of risk
should be considered at least modate we
should be respectful of the potential
for things that we don't know being
detrimental especially when there's
long-term concerns regarding
neurotoxicity bone mineral density
issues and a lack of information of how
estrogen levels are affected locally at
the tissue level again we can only
measure the serum amount which is the
proxy for local activity and we don't
know even if you just modulate your
estrogen a little bit in the serum
what's that going to do at different
tissue sites in the body you're going to
find out and I don't W recommend being
the guinea pig for that experiment
personally so I'm just going to present
the Devil's Advocate side to this as
well so while there's no evidence that
aromates inhibition is safe or
beneficial as I said before there is
equally no evidence that it is toxic or
dangerous or in that uh scenario whether
the dose makes the poison so I'm I'm
going to throw out the other side of the
argument there and I think it comes down
to the individual practitioner and
patient stance on the concept of is it
guilty until proven innocent or is it
innocent until proven guilty and what I
think pharmaceutical uh sorry what I
believe that Pharmaceuticals should
differ from in that perspective as
opposed to the law is that it should be
guilty until proven innocent these
things should be assumed unsafe until
they're proven safe because they are an
unnecessary intervention into your
health again my opinion so this is an
important one and this is something that
comes up a lot for me as a health coach
you know particularly working with these
guys on their behaviors on their getting
their lifestyle together on discussing
and improving mental health is that I
believe that trt takes months and years
to sufficiently androgenized a male
especially if he's not had optimal
testosterone levels before and that men
who believe that they are quote unquote
genetic aromatized simply need to be
patient while allowing trt to take full
effect but also to allow themselves time
to do the work that needs to be done we
say trt takes time to work it also takes
time to do the work that you need to do
so you may need to adjust your protocol
and lifestyle accordingly when you're
starting off maybe you need to come in
with a lower dose maybe you need to do
more frequent injections maybe you need
to use transcrotal cream maybe you need
to assess the situation that you're in
to get to the point that you can
optimally tolerate the testosterone dose
that you need but you also need to
understand that it's going to take more
than 12 to 16 weeks to adopt the traits
the values and attitudes the identity
the muscular all these all these
muscular sorry all these things that
you're expecting from the treatment to
turn you into the man you want to be it
takes more than 12 to 16 weeks of
exposure to androgens to do that and one
thing that I see a lot is that men who
don't subjectively feel masculine enough
whatever that means to them they see the
solution to that being reducing the
feminine side of the equation with an
aromatase inhibitor and I see the logic
I do but it just doesn't work like them
so I also believe that efforts and
interventions if we're going to be
making efforts and interventions should
be focused on resolving the root cause
issue of what is suspected to be leading
to this you know potential excessive
aromatization rather than just focusing
on treating the symptoms I believe the
focus on estrogen management should be
healthfully optimizing Liver Health and
lifestyle to handle environmental
xenoestrogen exposure rather than
limiting endogenous asadal production so
what I mean by this is that if you're
going to do something for optimizing
your Androgen to estrogen ratio you look
at what the foundational factors are
that are driving up inflammation in your
body because estrogen is naturally made
as an anti-inflammatory it's like
cortisol if you're stressed it's not
cortisol's fault your body's making
cortisol because you're stressed so if
your body's up regulating aromatase it's
not just because you're born broken and
your body's just pumping out estrogen
because you're genetically defective
it's probably because there's an
inflammatory condition going on
underneath and you need to actually work
with the body not on the body in trying
to resolve
that okay part two HCG again I've picked
all the most controversial areas today
so I'm sure that if this goes on YouTube
down the track everyone in the comments
is going to be crying and blowing up
I'll save you some time if youve made it
this far I'm not going to read the
comments so HCG is one of the most
polarizing topics in trt should be on
trt which has sparked borderline cult
religious like debates again people get
really emotionally in Ed in what
hormones other people take that they
don't know on the Internet it's weird so
in reality HCG is not as universally
well tolerated as people who promote its
use seem to believe now this may be due
to individual confirmation bias or it
may be incentivized to profit further
off each individual treatment this is
something that I see a lot my undergrad
degree is in marketing and I can tell
you that one of the most most effective
marketing strategies of all time is
creating a problem that you didn't know
you had and selling you the solution
especially if we can use fear to shut
down reasoning and impulse control so I
can also assure you that it is far more
profitable from a business standpoint to
sell 100 people three medications than
to sell three people uh sorry 300 people
one medication it is and I see this
happening all the time it's testosterone
HCG and an AI which is like fries and
coke with your burger at McDonald's
and this is massively increasing profit
margins per patient but what it is not
doing is actually focusing on what the
individual needs which in a lot of cases
is not HCG because I'm going to get to
why that is shortly so I have found that
the majority of the voices online who
promote HCG as a must and I'm not saying
the people who say that there are
benefits to using HCG because there can
be and there are but the people who are
promoting this as a must have for trt if
you go on trt you must use HCG or else I
haven't found anyone with this
perspective who's not selling it I
haven't found that and concurrently I
found that health coaches and providers
who have a more balanced perspective on
it like what I'm going going to present
to you today tend to be financially
independent of the patients medication
purchases so HCG is touted as a
lutenizing hormone memetic and this
increases my blood pressure because it's
nonsense so mimetic means mimicking
doing the same thing HCG does not do the
same thing as lutenizing hormone
does serotonin and LSD buy into the same
receptors LSD does very different things
than what serotonin does so if two
things bind to the same receptor it
doesn't make them memetics so HCG is a
lutenizing hormone receptor Agonist the
actual lutenizing hormone receptor is
actually called the LH HCG receptor in
full because both of these hormones buy
into the receptor but they do not do the
same thing if they did a woman would
just make more lutenizing hormone when
she was pregnant there is a reason why
HCG is made because it does different
stuff to lutenizing hormone so it is not
a mtic it agonizes the receptor and it
also does agonize the lutenizing hormone
receptors in the testicles and
stimulates the LC cells absolutely it
does we know that full well but what
else does it do differently to
lutenizing hormone in men we have
absolutely no idea there are a couple of
Articles and research papers
distinguishing the difference and
actually identifying the perspective of
HCG as an LH memetic as a gross
misunderstanding of the clinical
outcomes of these hormones but they are
not the same thing and they are not
interchangeable and I think that this is
one of the main reasons why a lot of men
don't tolerate HCG is the thing that
makes HCG different from lutenizing
hormone is why they're not tolerating
but I'm going to get to that a bit more
in in a sec so HCG is not natural to men
even in the micro do approaches that we
use to maintain testicular function on
trt now someone might come around and
say well actually men do make HCG in a
very small minuscule amount so it is
technically bioidentical okay tick boox
well done but in the doses that we're
talking about here it is not
bioidentical but the doses that we
typically use for trt as an adjunct are
100 to 150 units a day or 250 to 300
units either every other day or three
times weekly or 500 units twice a week
I'm sure there are some people who are
still practicing with, 1500 units once a
week but I think that's become a bit
outdated so somewhere within the
ballpark of a th000 units or less in two
to three divided doses tends to be the
norm with some guys doing uh daily shots
so I'm going to present some arguments
for and against so these are not all the
arguments for so Arguments for is
avoiding acquired organ failure where
possible is always optimal I think that
that's common sense right smaller
testicles are not the preference for the
majority of men maybe I'm just speaking
for myself but although test testicle
size is not make or break we're not
talking about impacting the size or
functionality of the penis that would be
a very different discussion but I think
most guys can agree that small testicles
are not
preferable so many men report
substantially improved energy well-being
libido and sexual function while
utilizing HCG I have seen guys go on HCG
and they're like the lights came on I've
got so much more energy I every
parameter that they were looking to
improve
improves and a very important point with
this is that we do not know the systemic
role of lutenizing hormone outside the
testes in men that well we do know that
there are lutenizing hormone receptors
systemically in the brain in the spine
Etc but we actually don't really know
that well what they do it hasn't been
that well studied and as a consequence
of this we do not know what will happen
if we stop stimulating these hormone
receptors chronically over the the
course of a man's
life so arguments against HCG is simply
not well tolerated by a substantial
subset of men this is the most important
part this is where we have to come to a
balanced perspective on HCG is that I
think it is incorrect to say that it is
mandatory for all men to use on trt
simply for this reason that there is a
decent subset I would say 30 to 50% of
guys react terribly to HCG on trt it's
that simple so hcg's differing effects
from lutenizing hormone outside of
Simply the longer half life of beta HCG
and the increase stimulation of thyroid
and
cyclic is simply not well studied or
known we don't know why these guys are
reacting so badly to HCG we don't know
why so we know some of what HCG does in
men we know what it does for the
testicles we know what it does for
fertility but we don't know what we
don't know all of what it does we have
no idea and we know that it's not well
tolerated by some men just go on Reddit
and you'll find that out so HCG produc
produces intolerable severe negative
symptoms for men who do not respond well
to it even in low doses I've seen guys
trial 10 IU of HCG a day 15 IU of HCG a
day which has been shown in some studies
to actually stimulate the testicles we
thought maybe they're just hyper
sensitive to it or maybe they just need
more time to adjust to it you know to
write it out no so HCG again these are
just little things to put in the cons
column but they're worth bringing up HCG
is not travel friendly or shelf stable
uh and it's not bioidentical to men
Beyond Trace Amounts and HCG adds a
complicating variable to tr so they're
kind of like the icing on the top for
the
cons so this is what I would consider a
balanced perspective and this is my
personal perspective
so and and this is maybe I'm just
creating more questions than I'm
answering here and if that's the case
sorry but this is the Crux of the
argument for me is that we do not know
whether it is better to shut down
testicular function while on trt or to
keep them stimulated by using a female
pregnancy hormone we don't know which
one of those outcomes is going to be
better we don't so it may be difficult
for some men to discern whether HCG is
helping or hindering them if they
started the treatment concurrently if
you feel like crap and testosterone
makes you feel 100 points better but HCG
makes you feel 50 points worse well
you've still netted 50 points points of
improvement so it's difficult to know if
you start them together if you actually
have responded well to HCG or not
so the other thing that I think is
important to note and this may burst
some people's bubble is fertility is
much more complex than simply using a
maintenance dose of HCG and this idea of
HCG as an insurance policy to prevent
infertility I think is drastically
oversimplified and completely misleading
if that was the case which I'm going to
discuss in the next section we wouldn't
need to use fertility protocols we could
just use the HCG protocol
so the most important part here as I've
said a few times is many men simply do
not tolerate HCG and they feel
significantly better without it so some
men benefit from HCG and some men don't
and if this is the case and I think most
people can agree on this then this means
that not all men should use HCG and
therefore HCG is not a mandatory adjunct
to trt I think that's better so a couple
of other things to consider is that
lutenizing hormone receptor stimulation
and I covered this to death in part
one it's not the only stimulating
pathway for the enzyme that converts uh
cholesterol into PR alone called CP 11
A1 it's not if it was every man on trt
monotherapy would be deficient in
progesterone pregnant alone DHEA
cortisol they're not this is not the
only thing that stimulates this pathway
and essentially given that we've
fulfilled the end role of
steroidogenesis with testosterone and
estrogen maybe a little bit less of that
stimulation in the pathway is actually a
biological process of the body restoring
balance in homeostasis makes sense so I
believe that men should not be forced or
made to feel afraid if they don't take a
medication which has not been studied in
the format that it's being prescribed
HCG as an adjunct to trt in these kind
of doses is not studied it's not
evidence-based medicine
and therefore men should not feel afraid
or guilty or like there's something
wrong with them if they're not taking
HCG with trt it's not something that's
actually backed by the literature so
every study as I said before about the
estrogen thing showing the benefits of
trt did not involve using HCG so all the
benefits that we know that testosterone
does are not going to vanish if you
don't use HCG it's nonsense so it's also
important to consider that a lot of the
mechanistic theory which is discussed
online around the steroidogenic Cascade
makes the Assumption and
oversimplification that HCG and
lutenizing hormone are the same thing
they're not so this doesn't show up too
well on my black background but this is
just pulled straight from Wikipedia this
is the steroidogenic Cascade where at
the top you've got cholesterol and
you've got pregnanolone and then over to
the right it goes to Progesterone and
corticosteroids and then South it goes
to DHEA and then across to the right
testosterone dihydrotestosterone and
estrogens this is the sex hormone cascet
now this diagram is often taken far too
literally and this is a diagram for
illustrative purposes for explaining a
concept this term of Upstream hormones
is metaphorical it's not literal the
these arrows that you see connecting
these hormones they're not just like
rivers that hormones run down like water
and the production and facilitation of
hormones by endocrine and paracrine
systems is far more complicated and
nuanced than this if it wasn't we could
just turn on the the taps with HCG and
then pour in a bunch of pregnant alone
and then all the pathways would back
fill it's not actually how it works so
in my experience you know just what I've
observed around a third of men
experience debilitating anxiety and
negative symptoms and side effects from
HCG including worse in sexual function
anxiety water retention mood
disturbances even rashes digestive
issues isues other immune related
symptoms from HCG and it's not fixed by
reducing the dose or adjusting to the
medication over a period of week so a
third of people on HCG tend to get
really bad side effects now I believe
this is just my opinion that this is due
to an immunological reaction to a female
pregnancy hormone which has no place
being in male biology men cannot get
pregnant sorry for the I know that that
might be controversial but a
physiological amount of a female
pregnancy hormone doesn't really have a
place in male biology and I think it
makes sense why the immune system might
react badly to them so the other thing
to consider is that HCG likely crosses
the blood brain barrier and potentially
has psychoactive effects in and of
itself potentially outside of what it's
doing Downstream from the lutenizing
hormone receptor because we simply do
not know what's going on so that's just
my
theory so although it's not known why or
how I presented my theory but that's not
fact is HCG is not tolerated by a good
chunk of men and it seems to revert them
back to their hypogonadal pret trt state
so it may be having some kind of
anti-androgenic effect potentially via
progesterone Pathways which is again
just my opinion I've also noticed about
a third of guys seem to not really
notice any subjective difference from
HCG aside from just increased testicle
size and then about a third of get what
I mentioned before the other end of the
spectrum the dramatically improved sense
of well-being sexual function energy and
libido and when I spoke at uh at the
Silverback Summit uh that that Steven
mentioned before uh with Dr Adam
Hotchkis he gave similar uh observations
in his experience it was about a third
bad a third neutral and a and a third uh
very positive
so I recommend and again this is my
recommendation to my clients to initiate
a trial of HCG 6 to 12 months after
you've started trt ascertain a
subjective Baseline of what testosterone
in isolation is doing for
you but I also think that if it works
great for you when you're not having any
issues that you don't need to complicate
it by adding an HCG so give it time to
see how how it's working get a
subjective Baseline for going okay this
is how I feel I'm X out of 10 and then
if I add in HCG for a trial period of of
a week to a month does it make me feel
better or does it make me feel worse and
then you can adjust your strategy
potentially for fertility which we're
going to discuss
next down the track so if you are going
to use HTG it is best administered
either every other day or three times a
week at a minimum ideally daily due to
its short half life of about 36 hours so
I recommend moving trt to every other
day or three times a week to make it
easier so that you can just take your
trt and your HCG on the same days and if
you need to increase inreasing your HCG
dose daily just to make your life a bit
easier so it's also important to
consider that HCG causes a drastic
increase in testosterone for some guys
mild increases for other guys and no
changes for some as well so before
people go oh well maybe that's why some
people feel great on HCG haven't found
that to be correlated personally so it's
very important that if you do initiate
HCG that you monitor your testosterone
levels because you may need to adjust
your trt dose down the track but because
the response to HCG is inconsistent I
personally don't think the trt dose
should be reduced in anticipation of the
levels going up with HCG I think that
that is wishful thinking and I think
that it's better to introduce HCG and
monitor symptoms and bloods at regular
intervals throughout treatment so HCG
maximally stimulates lutenizing hormone
receptors at 250 unit dosing therefore
going Beyond this is not necessary and I
find that this dose three times per week
is adequate to produce the desire
outcome although some people might want
to use a bit less and some people might
want to use a bit more depending on how
you respond so this brings us to
fertility
so if trt was an effective
contraceptive it would be the most
popular method of birth control in the
world it's not for a reason and I have a
joke and I think my joke is hilarious
it's uh what do you call the guy on trt
who thought it was birth control and the
answer is Dad so while trt will
absolutely impact and complicate
fertility in many men I would argue the
majority will have an impact it it would
be strange if the majority didn't have
some degree of impact on fertility
parameters when using trt it doesn't
make everyone in Fertile this is a myth
so often the underlying root cause of
hypogonadism is equally complicating the
fertility and patients are unknowingly
subfertile infertile prior to beginning
trt
if you are an obese alcoholic eating
junk food and not exercising and your
testosterone levels are in the gutter it
is very unlikely that you are super
fertile at the same time so it's also
important to recognize that trt does
result in Asus spermia which is the
fancy term for no sperm but it's not a
guarantee and the first point of call
for fertility should be to check where
your sperm count is ideally you'd also
check your sperm count before you start
trt so that you and have realistic
expectations and an understanding of how
your fertility changes in response to
treatment but sometimes that ship haset
so fertility protocols will allow men to
restore their individual fertility
capacity so if you have been unfortunate
enough to have testicular cancer or a
severe testical injury in the past your
response to a fertility treatment is
only going to bring you back to what you
can restore so it's going to be
individual so it means if there are
complications present for fertility like
ssris obesity drug and alcohol use
prolonged history of poor health
anabolic steroid abuse Etc fertility
protocols will only provide the results
a man could achieve at his PR at his pre
trt State we can't it's not magic it's
not fertility medications are
unfortunately not a Panacea for
fertility they are a tool so it's
imperative that men focus on passing on
and this is my opinion on the healthiest
best version of their genetic footprint
rather than just focusing on
successfully impregnating their wife so
men must work with the fertility
protocol as diet lifestyle Baseline
Health factors are absolutely at play in
the end outcome both in terms of the
fertility and the health of the child so
in instances where a man is infertile on
trt and this is just what I've observed
so let's say a guy goes on T te mon a
therapy and he comes back at Asus
spermic it's uncommon that the doses of
HCG that we spoke about before will
bring him to Optimal sperm parameters
alone now there will be outliers
absolutely I am not refuting that it is
impossible for this to happen but if
someone has been rendered infertile by
trt generally they will need an
additional adjunct whether it's a mega
dose of HCG or the use of fs and I much
prefer the letter to actually get
fertility working so this contradicts
this myth that adding in HCG is this
perfect insurance policy for preventing
infertility because again the doses that
are prescribed in addition to trt are
not evidence-based for actually fixing
this problem so higher doses of HCG have
been studied and successfully restore
sperm counts 1500 IU three times a week
sometimes I believe it even goes up to
5,000 units three times a week or maybe
even more than that but these doses are
much more prone to causing side effects
they're also expensive and will carry
unknown Health outcomes long term so I
caution against using Mega doses of HCG
prophylactically for fertility and it's
also just not well tolerated and this is
just my two cents each to their own do
what you like it's your body I don't
care but I don't think it's healthy for
a man to be able to piss on a pregnancy
test year round and get a positive
result I don't think that's good for
mental heal so hcg's effect on fertility
in higher doses is due to its spill over
to agonizing the FSH receptor but given
that FSH is available this is a much
better option to use for fertility
because it's bioidentical it's the
bioidentical thing we need to do what we
want it to do
so bioidentical FSH to stimulate the FSH
receptor and HCG in a low dose to
stimulate the lutenizing hormone
receptor is extremely effective and can
be utilized for a period of 12 to 16
weeks often you don't need that long and
I'm saying 12 to 16 weeks because this
is the time it often takes to produce
the optimal sperm parameters it's not
like you can only run it for 12 to 16
weeks you can run it for as long as you
need to conceive will allow a man to
restore his Baseline fertility State
while he remains on trt this is huge
because it means that guys don't have to
crash their testosterone levels and
become hypogonadal feel like crap have
their health go into a a very poor state
and also massively reduce their sex
drive and sex function which is integral
for achieving the outcome that they're
trying to achieve which is conception so
what this allows for and I've I've used
my words very specifically here because
I didn't say it mimics LH and FSH it
allows for a similar lutenizing hormone
receptor and follicle stimulating
hormone receptor signaling profile as if
the man were to stop trt but without the
reoccurrence of the hypogonadism so it's
like like you're getting the same signal
to the testicles or as as similar as we
can do as if you'd stop the trt but you
can maintain your optimal testosterone
levels and I think I'm not saying this
is evidence-based but I believe based on
what I've observed in mechanistic theory
that not only is this just going to be a
less awful experience you can avoid
suffering and you know depending on how
much you value your subjective suffering
or what the impact that will be on your
family career mental health Etc you know
that's all important too but I think
it's also massively beneficial to the
epigenetic signaling for your son or
daughter because healthy people have
healthier children we know that so FSH
can be run alongside trt longterm in
maintenance dosages if you want to but
it's really expensive so for most people
this is going to be cost prohibitive
so men need to make their own decision
around how they want to approach this
fertility is Big having a family in the
future is Big fertility is a sensitive
topic there is not a one-sized fits-all
and strangers on the internet are not
the people to give you advice on what
you should do here you need to discuss
this with someone like one of the staff
at mer Health to actually work out what
the best point of call for you is here
and how to best move ahead to get the
outcome that is going to be suitable for
you so as many men respond to HCG
subjectively poorly as I mentioned
before if HCG causes you negative
symptoms that it may be wiser to forego
fertility treatments until it comes time
to
conceive however if HCG is well
tolerated and produces benefits then I'm
going to say and I've highlighted the
word may it may be more beneficial to
use HCG in a maintenance dose in the
intrum and then use a full fertility
protocol when it comes time to conceive
if you need that so you can basically
create an if this then that scenario and
go okay I Tri HCG on my trt it made me
feel like dog [__] so I'm just going to
use this down the line with FSH to
reactivate my fertility or I tried HCG
it makes me feel a million bucks or I
don't feel any different on it but it
brings back my fertility size sorry my
testicle size I'm planning to conceive
in the next couple of years so I'm going
to make the choice to stay on HCG in the
inim because this may and I'm not saying
that it will but it may mean that when I
do come time to do the fertility
protocol that I may respond to that
better I do not personally think that
HCG is a defining Factor based on what
I've seen in the fertility protocols
that I've worked with my clients on as
to whether someone will or will not
respond to uh the fertility protocol
down the line what I have seen be the
determining factor is anabolic steroid
abuse as well as issues with diet and
lifestyle which would render them
infertile if they were off trt and I
think those two are bigger factors than
how long someone has been on trt so but
most importantly as I said men should
assess their individual symptomatic
response to maintenance doses of HCG
first and then work out with your
provider or your doctor how to best move
forward so again these are just my
opinions I do not recommend Clomid or
novedex novedex sorry to moxin for
fertility due to one negative side
effects just not feeling like [__] is
good
but well studied effects on epigenetic
signaling when used by women for
conception we know that Clomid massively
impacts the outcome of twins so we don't
know what else this is going to do at an
epigenetic level but we know it does
something so the effects on epigenetics
when these medications are used by men
have not been studied so we don't know
what they're going to do and with the
availability of bioidentical FSH the
only advantage that these medications
offer is being more budget friendly and
you trigger warning the truth may hurt
but if you can't afford FSH you can't
afford a child so FSH can be used at 50
to 150 units three times a week to
successfully restore sperm parameters in
12 to 16 weeks 150 IU three times a week
is the most beneficial and well studied
dose however many guys who I've worked
with have used 50 IU three times a week
and have had success many have also
needed the 1503 times a week so
HCG when used concurrently because we've
already fulfilled the requirements of
FSH we don't need to have that spillover
effect from HCG anymore we can simply
use HCG at 250 units daily which will
maximally stimulate intratesticular
testost reproduction and therefore LH
receptor activation because the FSH is
present so 150 units of FSH three times
a week with 250 units of HTG daily and I
prefer daily because now we're using
more per week and again Peaks and
troughs cause side effects with
treatments so daily is going to be best
if you can't deal with the daily
inconvenience of doing an insulin
syringe shot first thing in the morning
you cannot deal with the inconvenience
of having a child or a pregnant wife so
daily dosing is recommended and Men Who
react badly to HCG you might get away
with lower dosing like 100 to 150 units
per day but you'll need to discuss this
with your doctor and run blood work as
you go and sperm uh sperm accounts as
you go to see how you're
responding
so that's
[Music]
all